[Music]
so
hello good evening good day everybody
how are you doing i hope you're all
doing very well welcome to the latest
episode of the ask a widget show today
we discuss science astrophysics
technology and all that wonderful stuff
great to see you all let's see who all
is there with us let's see um
vladimir adityanath
mr jesus
rahul crazy brain shweta priyanshi
thomas vishal purobi
sneha sayan zen mehul
[Laughter]
paradigm shift and lots of other people
great to have you all with us let's see
some more people are i keshav ram sameer
janani lagera
online divyang joseph stalin
abhishek mohit lucifer morningstar ri
abhijit kamat
rtk and lots of people
great to have you all on this tonight's
show
it's night here where i am
and with that said let us get into the
questions we are discussing science and
all that fun stuff
let's see the first question what is the
first question for today
okay gihan jain says if nuclear
submarines can be made then why is it
taking so much time to make nuclear
power based aeroplanes and there's a
related question of with that what are
your thoughts on nuclear microreactors
are they viable and stable alternate
power source in resource scarce regions
for long-term operation
that's from pranav and the first
question about nuclear aeroplanes is by
jihan jain
so on a slightly tangential note it
reminds me of this
this wonderful piece of logic you know
uh
it
it is said that uh
submarines
are safer than airplanes
so why are submarines safer than
airplanes
because there are far more airplanes in
the sea than submarines in the air
logic
right so that's why submarines are safer
than airplanes anyhow let's come back to
the question
so if nuclear submarines can be made why
is it taking so much time to make
nuclear power based aeroplanes
it could be possible the thing is a
nuclear
the thing about airplanes is that
sometimes they tend to malfunction any
piece of mechanical equipment any piece
of technology can malfunction
now if you are in a
you have an airplane if it malfunctions
unfortunately it crashes this happens
from time to time a few crashes per year
we witness right in various parts of the
world
that's what that's what happens now if
you have a nuclear reactor on an
airplane and it unfortunately for
whatever reason crashes you're gonna
have a disaster
unless you make the nuclear reactor so
durable and so uh
so hardy that it doesn't break open and
leak out it's its contents right so
that's always a problem when you have an
airplane that falls from the sky for
whatever reason from a few kilometers up
in this in the sky you're gonna have a
massive impact right and that impact
could cause a catastrophe a nuclear
catastrophe if there is a nuclear
reactor on the airplane
so the the the solution
would be if you want a nuclear powered
plane first of all you would have to
miniaturize the reactor that's all it's
already a problem it's already a huge
technological challenge to miniaturize
nuclear reactors for submarines right if
you want to make a nuclear submarine if
you want to make it nuclear powered you
have to miniaturize the reactor in your
terrestrial i mean your regular reactors
the reactors can be as big as you want
them to be size is not an issue you can
make them large but for nuclear
submarines every single kilogram that
goes on to it matters
so to miniaturize it and miniaturizing
reactors just for nuclear submarines
itself is a huge technological challenge
very few nations have been able to
overcome this challenge solve the solve
the challenge i believe india is one of
those nations that have overcome the
challenge yes right
so uh
so it's already a challenge to make
reactors fit into new into submarines
now you want them to fit into aircraft
you're gonna have to miniatures
miniaturize them even further and i
think i don't think it's right now
within the
uh capabilities of any nation or any any
or any technology technological advance
to miniaturize uh nuclear reactors that
far
right
so that is the problem and so there are
two things first of all it's thus far
it's not been possible to make nuclear
reactors that small as far as we know
whatever information is in the public
domain from that i am saying that we
nobody has thus far developed the
capability to miniaturize nuclear
reactors that much and secondly there's
a problem for even if the aircraft
caches crashes for for some other
non-nuclear react reactor related reason
is going to fall down and it's going to
fall from a height of several kilometers
typically yeah the cruising altitude for
airliners commercial aircraft is
typically 10 11 12 kilometers around
around that that altitude
you have something falling from there
it's gonna break open the reactor unless
you make it really really strong and
durable which would need additional
weight which would which would defeat
the purpose of miniaturizing it so these
are the reasons
why it's not been why nobody has done it
as if i know the americans and even the
soviets had tried this they may have
tested this out nuclear powered uh
aeroplanes now see nuclear reactors can
certainly be carried in aircraft yeah if
you have large enough aircraft so you
could use that to power the aircraft
there's also the concept of nuclear
powered ram jets and scramjets right
so in a ramjet engine you are you first
accelerate the rocket or the missile or
whatever it is
to a certain i think mach 2 and beyond
at least mach 1 and then the supersonic
ingestion of air
powers the secondary motor which is a
ramjet right so you can have nuclear
power run jets instead of
chemical
chemical fuel powered ramjets and that
technology does exist it's been tested
out you have a reasonably small nuclear
reaction going on it
heats air to incredible
temperatures and that's what powers the
ramjet so it is certainly possible to do
it so so
if you have
a nuclear powered ramjet you could you
could use the same technology on
aircraft so the technology seems to
exist yes yes but because of these
concerns nobody wants to have flying
nuclear reactors right so that's the
reason why
it's not taking time it's that it's just
a little bit too hazardous people are
already scared of nuclear technology we
have one or two incidents that have
happened in the past the
three mile island incident chernobyl was
a disaster fukushima unfortunately it's
something that happened in 2011 that was
not nice yeah
so these these things scare people
nuclear technology is unfortunately
associated with the atomic bomb which is
a horrific weapon and that's why people
are scared and you know it's politically
like in a hot potato kind of thing using
nuclear technology on aircraft and all
that stuff people will be scared
there was this technology called nuclear
magnetic resonance imaging nmr imaging
they had to rebrand it and call it mri
magnetic resonance imaging it's the same
thing
they've just given it a new name
mri instead of nmr because nmr stood for
nuclear magnetic resonance imaging and
that scares the heebie jeebies out of
people
the the term nuclear so there are
multiple factors
that go behind this and that's why
nobody has taken this uh has done this
you know especially for commercial
aircraft but we do have certain nuclear
powered uh missiles i believe the
russians the the russians
announced that they have a
nuclear-powered cruise missile i think
they announced it in 2019 if i'm not
missing 2018 or 2019. so the technology
does exist but for these reasons it's
not been adopted widely maybe there are
some secret projects that are being run
by certain countries nations yeah that
would be
utilizing such technology but not as
it's not been announced or revealed or
made available in the public domain
right
and this is this associated question
about nuclear micro reactors are they a
viable and stable alternate power source
in resource cars regions or for long
term operation so when you talk about
nuclear micro reactors i mean one would
imagine a nuclear reactor that can be
carried on on a car
or or
something that well not not something
you can carry in a suitcase most likely
that would be really scary but yeah
something that can be transported by by
car
yeah and installed in homes
or or in buildings and that would power
the entire building for the foreseeable
future you know as long as the nuclear
fuel lasts and the fuel obviously would
be replaceable and so on so and so forth
uh it is certainly something that can
happen that only the only constraint is
that first of all nuclear fuel is
extremely expensive euro it's typically
uranium you could also use thorium you
can also use plutonium these uh
nuclear fuels are extremely uh
expensive
and they have multiple uses i mean you
put a nuclear reactor into civilian
hands god knows who else will get get
their hands on it so it it's something
that needs extremely tight security
and that's why it's only used for
typically for military and
other purposes you can have nuclear
directors that power
a city and all but those nuclear
directors are very heavily guarded right
there's a very very strong security
multiple layers of security so typically
it's something you don't want
the nuclear fuel essence especially to
fall into the wrong hands it's something
that lots of people would love to get
their hands on and all kinds of shady
and dodgy people and governments
we don't want that to happen so that is
the primary reason why nuclear micro
directors haven't made their way into
people's homes and people buildings and
stuff like that the technology i mean if
you can miniaturize a nuclear reactor
and put it on a nuclear submarine if you
can have a nuclear-powered ramjet on a
cruise missile
the technology certainly exists to
miniaturize it that far and make a micro
reactor right
so i don't see it uh gaining wide
adoption because of the security
concerns that go along with this yeah
you would
i mean you can make a micro reactor
installed in the building in a house but
you would need 24 by 7 by 365 armed
guards and multiple layers of security
to safeguard that and that is something
that's going to cost you a lot yeah and
the nuclear director itself will cost a
lot so it's not financially feasible
thus far as far as
where we are in the 21st century maybe
100 years down the line maybe i don't
know maybe even 20 is not down the line
if you can solve the security issues and
things like that yeah
so it is certainly something that can be
done but the nuclear fuel is very
expensive
and there are these security issues so
what we can do is we can have multiple
nuclear reactors in our nation and that
can power the nation i believe france
for instance gained
i think about 70 of its electricity
needs are met by nuclear power nuclear
power station nuclear reactors right
so you don't need nuclear micro reactors
you can have massive reactors that
output a massive amount of electricity
that can power an entire city an entire
state and
maybe a significant percentage of an
entire nation's power supply that can be
done so that's why we go big rather than
small
that is the reason why it is so and
that's why i don't see it uh
gaining a lot of currency you know micro
reactors for these reasons
all right next question
okay sort of says nick brown a renowned
researcher in the field of psychology
says said that you can't turn science
into technology unless the science is
solid and repeatable that is correct
then how did fields like psychiatry
social studies behavioral sciences etc
flourish if behaviors the very root of
all these fields are still not very
understood
see technology i i totally agree with
what nick brown i don't know about him
but if he said this he's absolutely
right technology uh science can be
turned into technology only if it is
very well understood and you can repeat
it on demand right if you can replicate
the phenomenon again and again and again
in a reliable manner in a foolproof
manner on demand then you can turn
science into technology
so you have so many examples of that you
know
laptops they build laptops and
telecommunications they are all built on
the on top of quantum technology and so
on and so forth so we have all these
technologies which are reliable and
repeatable right so science can be
turned into technology only when it is
that way now
i do not consider psychiatry to be a
science
it's voodoo i know some people will get
upset well
well that's just what it is don't agree
with me that's fine feel free to
disagree social sciences are even less
of science than psychiatry
behavioral sciences i mean
these are not sciences just because we
put science at the end of social doesn't
make it a science some people call
themselves i'm a social scientist what a
joke there is
there is no such thing as social science
it's not a science it's social voodoo
and psychiatry again
psychiatry is about understanding the
the human mind yes
now we know to the best of our
understanding from all these centuries
of
understanding
the human body and the human behavior
and all that we know
that the the seat of the mind the seat
of consciousness is the human brain
i mean you can cut off somebody's arm
the person's consciousness will not
change
yeah people can suffer all kinds of
injuries arms legs etc their
consciousness remains intact it's only
when the
brain is
is is injured that there are altered
states of consciousness or if somebody
suffers catastrophic brain damage the
consciousness evaporates disappears with
the best of our knowledge
so the seat of consciousness the seat of
the mind is the brain
now
tell me about any scientific there's any
medical discipline let's say cardiology
in cardiology you scan the heart you
take detailed uh you know you you image
the heart through various various means
you know by injecting dyes into the
bloodstream
and and you you can do a ct scan or
whatever right you can do mra scans of
the heart to see if the heart is not
working fine you can see where there are
blockages and all so you take detailed
images of the organ that you are
studying and that you're trying to heal
when it comes to various other organs
whether it's bones or whatever you take
detailed you you image the organs you're
studying and you're trying to heal when
it comes to psychiatry do they ever take
brain scans do they ever ever look at
what's wrong with the brain structurally
physically no
no they don't do that
they they just uh
infer what may be happening and diagnose
things and that's why psychiatry is such
a poor science
uh i am sure there are a few good
psychiatrists who actually do it
you know take the thing seriously and do
it in a scientific manner yeah i know
some some comments are coming in that's
all right that's all right some people
will not like it but this is my
perspective psychiatry is not a rigorous
science psychiatry is still hand waving
in voodoo
and that's why most psychiatrists don't
really uh produce
any results for their patients yeah
patients may feel that something has
happened that's mostly the placebo
effect yeah
they they prescribe various drugs
chemicals etc based on very very vague
clusters of symbols same symptoms
psychiatrists typically look for certain
clusters of symptoms yeah
unfortunately those clusters of symptoms
can be caused by a variety
of pathologies
some could be mental some could be
actually structural somebody fell down
as a kid when they were three years old
they damaged their brain no one knows
that there is brain damage and that
persists and that manifests itself in a
is a certain cluster of symptoms
and so on so forth so you need to
actually scan the brain first of all no
psychiatrist that i know of does this
maybe one percent of psychiatrists must
be doing it so they don't even look at
the organ they are trying to heal and
then they call themselves medical
professionals it's a joke psychiatry as
of today is mostly a joke yeah it's not
a reliable science social studies is
it's just voodoo yeah
it's uh you know i have nothing against
studying society but you have to do it
in a in a scientific manner you do it
statistically
you have something called statistical
mechanics in physics where you very look
at the large scale behavior of gases and
thermodynamic systems and things like
that it is a rigorous science
you can do you can apply similar
principles
to the study of society you you look at
it statistically and you can
see how behaviors emerge how various uh
how how things change of society evolves
over time and you can look at certain
parameters but you have to do it
statistically rigorously mathematically
scientifically social studies today most
of it is about writing
god knows what kind of papers based on
people's whims and fancies it's a joke
i do not consider social studies to be a
science whatsoever
in behavioral science once again it's
about you know
looking at various clusters of behaviors
and clusters of symptoms and all it's
it's in a way it's in a way similar to
psychiatry you know
and
yeah so i do not consider any of these
fields to be scientific in nature and if
some people don't like it well they can
keep coping
okay q q
whatever yeah i don't know what the name
is okay the question is what's your take
on homeopathy is it useless and the
doctors are fooling people why do so
many people claim that they got
permanently cured and refer others their
medicine has a weird way of working is
it if it's that highly diluted why does
it smell strong like alcohol
if it's true it has to be placebo effect
what's your take on this yeah right
right right there is something called
there is a term right that people use
homeopathic dose which means those that
so dilute that it's insignificant
so listen
homeopathy is something that i believe
emerged in the 19th century in germany i
think yeah
and at that time science was i mean the
field of medical medicine has not even
taken off we did not even understand
where diseases emerge from most of them
emerge from from microorganisms and
organisms and all that we did not know
that yet yeah
so um
so homeopathic emerged in the 19th
century and it kind of worked for some
people and even today it's still a thing
and there are lots of homeopathic
practitioners and so on so a couple of
days ago i had this uh
interesting discussion with dr sidwary
who's a neuroscientist he said that
romyopathy actually works for many
people and the way it works
is it's not because of the doses or
whatever but because of the the way the
doctor interacts with the patient so
typically when you go to a regular
doctor in india especially when you when
you're paying less and when you go to a
hospital with 5 million patients waiting
in line the doctor will typically speak
to you for like 60 seconds or 120
seconds to three minutes at most
very brief interaction and he or she
will prescribe whatever they think is
right based on whatever symptoms you're
exhibiting and you're done out
and then the medicine is is what we call
allopathic medicine right
in the case of homeopathic doctors the
doctors will take their time in
interacting with the patient they will
ask him how was your day
how are your kids how's your wife how
are things how's your work life going
and so on so forth they're gonna take a
good 30 to 45 minutes interacting with
the patient
asking very detailed questions and the
patient feels that the doctor cares
you know so and that is the primary
reason why the treatment works because
the patient actually trusts the doctor
and it is the trust that that causes
that what you would call a psychosomatic
kind of reaction you know
and that's again that again is a
manifestation of the placebo effect so
it's not the medicine that works it's
that's just the fact that the three the
the tree the doctors
uh treat the patient in a certain way
and the patients because of that they
end up really trusting the doctor and
when you trust a doctor even if they
give you a salt pill and you swallow it
you you're gonna feel that it's working
and the fact that you feel it's working
is going to activate certain healing
mechanisms in your
in your body yeah the body has the brain
can produce certain chemicals that that
can have pain killing effects and they
can make you feel better and all that
right so the placebo effect depends on a
variety of factors and it seems that the
the homeopathic practitioners have
cracked the code of how to induce a
placebo effect in patients right so the
medicines don't work if you
it if a if if an allopathic doctor were
to prescribe the homeopathic medicines
it's guaranteed that there will be no
effect the medicines won't work the the
treatment works only because
of the induced placebo effect the way
the doctors interact with the with that
patient the homeopathic practitioners
interact with the pressure patient
so to sum it up
the medicines whatever the medicines are
whatever the the pills or whatever is
they don't work
right they don't work it's the
it's just that they have figured out how
to induce a placebo effect in people and
maybe it works for some people but it's
certainly not not going to cure cancer
or some genuinely serious illnesses
you've got a cough or you've got a cold
or you've got some long-term chronic
problems that can be resolved by placebo
effect yeah it's going to work that way
i have no idea why does it smell like
alcohol i've never tried any homeopathic
treatment i don't know what it smells
like
i believe it's sugar pills with it i
don't know something infused in them
uh
typically i've seen those round little
pills that people ingest like seven
times a day or 87 times a day i don't
know what is it so i i don't mean to
disparage or or or demean something that
does indeed work for some people yeah
but it's not the
pills
that work it's not the so-called
medicines that work it's the
way they
interact with the patients that induces
a placebo effect and that's what causes
some people to get better it's not going
to make everybody get better yeah you've
got a heart disease you go to a
homeopathic doctor it's not going to
cure you please be sure of that you're
going to need treatment from a proper
cardiologist that could actually cure
you you get angiopathy or whatever it is
you know uh
bypass procedures or whatever in case
you have in case somebody has cardiac
issues and so on depending on what your
issues are
so that's how it is so homeopathy is
nothing but a way of inducing a placebo
effect and that works for some people
who have not very serious conditions for
other people it's not going to work so
be careful all right
next question
here we are
it's by swapnil what's the controversy
surrounding the creation of the darwaza
gas crater in turkmenistan
what chemical reaction has caused it to
be still on fire after 50 years of its
formation and will it ever get
extinguished
the darwaza crater let's take a look at
what this thing looks like
let me
google that up
there was a creator
there was a crater let me put that on
the screen so that you
can see what this
thing looks like the darwaza crater it's
something that's in turkmenistan it's a
gas crater let's see the images shall we
these are the images of this crater so
it's a crater it's a hole in the ground
essentially that is on fire it's been on
fire since
i think the 1970s so yeah around 50
years
about half a century and some people
have gone into it and so on so forth so
what's the story behind this is there
any controversy
right
so what is this thing it's in
turkmenistan in case you don't know what
turkmenistan let's go to the map yeah
let's let's do that as well
we have maps always
so let's go to turkmenistan where is
turkmenistan let's go to the map
turkmenistan is not far from india in
case you're wondering it's not really
far
it's north west of afghanistan which was
once
gandhar
so this here is turkmenistan and in here
somewhere somewhere in this territory of
turkmenistan you have the darwaza gas
crater
so now let's get that off the map of the
screen and what is this gas crater so uh
i believe the story uh see turkmenistan
in the 1970s until 19 until the early
1990s was part of the ussr the union of
soviet socialist republics yeah it was
part of the soviet union turkmenistan
so uh there are
gas resources
natural resources in turkmenistan
natural gas and petroleum etc to a
certain extent
so various soviet geologists were
scouring the length and the breadth of
the soviet union to to find more
uh such uh
reservoirs of uh petrochemicals of gas
natural gas and so on so they they were
doing some drilling some excavation work
some investigation work in turkmenistan
and then they found this big vein of gas
that was emitting a natural gas methane
and various
natural gas is a mix of various gases
combustible gases
and uh they were actually not looking
for natural gas they were looking for
petroleum or or something like that they
were looking for oil most likely
so that when they discovered gas it's
not what they wanted they did not have
any use for it they did not most likely
have the means to uh
means to collect it and use it for for
commercial purposes and energy
generation so what they did was they
decided to burn it off they thought it's
a small
it's a small pocket of gas gas or
whatever yeah so let's burn it off it'll
burn off in a few days maybe a week and
then we can move on with our work
they
set it on fire it is believed to be in
the 1970s yes satellite imagery does
seem to suggest it
it began in the 1970s so they set this
thing on fire and eventually the entire
gas the gas pocket collapsed and it
created this big crater uh which you can
see
let's put it again on the screen
so there was a dome on it which
collapsed and it gave rise to a big
crater as you can see
so this began in the 1970s it started
burning they thought it will burn out
the gas will get extinguished it will
burn out in a few days maybe a week
maybe a month maximum
and it's still burning
so that's what happened it looks like
it's a very deep well and very deep
reservoir reservoir of natural natural
gas
and it's burning and no one knows when
it will when it will be extinguished
whether it will be possible for it to
extinguish itself on its own naturally
or will some human intervention be
required
i believe the president of turkmenistan
uh gurban guli bhardi muhammadaf i think
that's his name
apologies if i got it wrong so i believe
the president of turkmenistan a few
years ago had ordered that this be
extinguished or whatever but clearly
thus far it's not happened is it
possible to extinguish it so i think the
the diameter of this thing is about 60
or 70 meters that's that's a massive
crater it's not small it's not a small
crater 60 70 meters is big as you can
see you can see human beings for scale
it's a reasonably massive crater and it
just keeps on burning it's not ex it's
not
turning off on its own now there are
other craters like there are other
examples of fires that keep burning i
believe there is something in azerbaijan
or armenia there is some some
fire that's been burning for about four
thousand years i think that's what uh
gave rise to the zoroastrian
tradition of keeping fires burning
forever you know
uh zero streams were worship fire agni
right so uh
so i think this this gas uh
this gas well in in armenia or
azerbaijan wherever it is that could
have been the root cause or or the or
the origin of this zoroastrian custom of
keeping fires alive you know for for
centuries
so there is one such example somewhere
there in the caucasus region
turkmenistan
sorry azerbaijan armenia where you have
a fire that's been burning for more than
4000 years
then in australia there's something
called a burning mountain if i'm amazing
let's let's google it is it burning
mountain australia
be you are in the burning mountain
mountain
australia
burning mountain striae so this here
is a mountain
that inside this mountain there is a
coal vein or coal seam or something
that has been burning for god knows how
long i don't know centuries perhaps
so even this thing has been burning for
a very long time maybe maybe more than a
thousand years
and it's it's a most likely a natural
fire
so you have these phenomena that take
place there's even been a natural
nuclear reactor somewhere in africa that
that existed that was active
more than a billion years ago so some
such phenomena occur naturally but in k
but in the case of the
turkmenistan crater it is something that
was
that was created artificially by
geologists who assumed
i would say a little naively that it
would burn out in a week's time there
was no
there was no evidence that it would it
would stop burning in a week's time so
they made the assumption the kind of
naive assumption that it's a small
pocket of gas it'll burn out on the zone
it's still burning
and
it may be possible to extinguish it
naturally so fire needs three things
it needs oxygen
it needs fuel
and it needs a heat source so in the
case of the turkmenistan gas whether
there was a gas well
the fuel is there natural gas right
oxygen is there the atmosphere which the
crater is directly exposed to and the
heat source was provided by the soviet
geologists so they ignited the fire and
it's still burning so the heat source is
there the fuel is there and the oxygen
is there so you want to kill the fire
you have to deprive it of one of these
three things the
natural gas there seems to be an
apparently inexhaustible reservoir of
gas so you're not going to be able to
cut that off
oxygen out there
that's one thing or the fire the fuel
now sorry the the temperature of the
fire the spark the spark is there the
i would say the easiest way
comparatively easiest way would be to
blanket it in sand or something which
would cut off the access to the oxygen
for the flames and that could maybe stop
it but then you would have all this
natural gas um escaping into the
atmosphere
um maybe they would want to take care of
that as well maybe by sealing the crater
so it's not an easy task
to switch off the fire and to seal of
the crater and stop the natural gas from
escaping so the question for the
government is is it worth doing it it's
gonna cost a lot of money
uh manpower to do that is it worth doing
it or can we just use the money for
something else you know the resources so
so that's where we have so there's no
real controversy as such this is what
happened
and it's something that that keeps on
going and i think it's kind of a tourist
attraction of sorts these days people
want to go there and have a photograph
there you know it's even been used as
one of this
one of the pit stops for a rally you
know car rally or whatever motorcycle
rally something so yeah it's become kind
of a tourist attraction it's one of the
attractions that you have in this nation
of turkmenistan people if they go to
turkmenistan they want to visit the
therwaza crater so maybe it's something
they
they may want to keep keep going perhaps
so it's for them to decide so there's no
controversy as such this is what
happened
shazam
says
what type of radiation is released by
mobile phones is it harmful
good question
so mobile phones where's mines it's not
here so mobile phones is something we
all carry we all carry it unfortunately
we carry 24x7 essentially these days
so
and and the mobile phones do
emit certain amounts of radiation and
that's why it's something that is of
utmost concern to most people hopefully
as to what sort of radiation is it
giving off is it harmful right so
there are see
the radiation we are talking about is
electromagnetic radiation photons we're
talking about photons electromagnetic
radiation now electromagnetic radiation
occurs in a spectrum
various frequencies frequency wavelength
with
two sides of the same coin
so there's a whole spectrum of
electromagnetic radiation and you could
crudely roughly
divide it into two parts ionizing
radiation and non-ionizing radiation so
what is ionizing radiation it is
radiation that is so energetic it can
knock electrons out of atoms it can
break chemical bonds it can damage dna
that is a scary radiation that's what we
don't want
because you have that next to you it's
going to mess up your internal structure
if it causes dna damage and mutations
that gives rise to cancers
so ionizing radiation is dangerous what
is ionizing radiation x-rays gamma rays
etc even ultraviolet radiation
ultraviolet light is is to some extent
ionizing radiation yeah ultraviolet rays
are dangerous they can cause skin cancer
that's why people with a very light skin
tone you know
white white skin
the ones who live in australia they have
a very high incidence of skin cancer
because australia is a very sunny place
and you have these people who don't
belong there who now have occupied the
place they're living there the white
people they've got very light skin
and that's
that's something that is unable to ward
off the electromagnetic radiation
especially the ultraviolet rays that do
make it through the atmosphere the
natives of australia they have very dark
skins that's why they are naturally
protected that's how they evolved over
60 70 000 years
so yeah okay so now coming back to
radiation emitted by mobile phones
what kind what manner of radiation is it
okay let me put something on the screen
you know what is the spectrum of
electromagnetic radiation so that it
will give you a good illustration of how
it is electromagnetic
radiation
let's put that on the screen let us see
the spectrum
google search electromagnetic spectrum
and then we do a wikipedia
we do a dive into wikipedia now for
wikipedia let me again remind you all
it's not entirely reliable but for the
sake of when it comes to science it's
more reliable than as opposed to history
so here if you can see
we have the electromagnetic spectrum so
we have ionizing radiation then you have
the visible
part of the spectrum and then you have a
low frequency radiation so when it comes
to visible light okay the light that we
can perceive with our eyes that's what
we can see right uh it's it's got a
wavelength of between 100 nanometers to
one millimeter yeah
uh
actually even not that
near infrared
so yeah you can see over here what the
visible spectrum is it's near the near
ultraviolet from one micrometer to 100
nanometers around that yeah then you
have ionizing radiation that starts from
the ultraviolet
to the extreme ultraviolet to soft
x-rays to hard excess to gamma rays
extremely
uh
high frequency and high energy
radiation so you can see how much energy
each photon carries 1.24 mev which is
gamma rays that's frightful
right extreme ultraviolet ray radiation
uh the photons have about 124 electron
volts of energy even that is a scary
yeah now when it comes to mobile phones
they give off
radio waves the the mobile phones work
in the radio frequency
uh spectrum
so it's typically a high frequency media
i'm not sure exactly which which part of
the radio wave frequency it uses but
it's typically not very high frequency
it's maybe high frequency medium or
whatever right
so mobile phones as far as we know as
far as we are told
the radiation that they release is very
small amounts of radio frequency
electromagnetic radiation and
mobile phones essentially are
radio sets yeah two-way radiuses that's
what they are and we need all these
cells you know
uh mobile cells these towers where you
can which act as uh transmitting
stations and that's how that's why
they're called cell phone because we
need these various cells in a particular
geographic region
uh so
so as far as we know from whatever
information is available in the public
domain the only radiation that mobile
phones release
is radio waves radio waves are not
ionizing radiation not by a far distance
radio waves are safe
okay so
so the thing is this the only way to
know for sure is to have radiation
detectors
you would need a geiger counter gm
counter or something and video
you know detectors of various kinds you
put that next to your mobile phone and
only then will you know for sure i mean
i these counters are not available in
the i mean you know
expensive and not readily available so i
have never done a test on my mobile
phone with what sort of radiation is it
releasing so what we do is we we trust
what the authorities say and what the
mobile manufacturers say they say that
it's radio frequency radiation which is
not a concern if it is only that
perfectly good no issues
and as far as we know
there are no radioactive elements in
mobile phones and if there are no
radioactive elements there should be no
ionizing radiation uh whether it's
extreme ultraviolet or x-rays or gamma
rays so
from what i can see from all the
information that i have seen in the
public domain it appears that uh mobile
phones are safe they only release they
only
uh work in the radio frequency
electromagnetic spectrum which is
safe which we know is safe
so that's what i can tell you
okay donggar singh johan says
how is it possible to hear sound from a
black hole um
okay so to answer this question first of
all we have to address the question of
what is sound
how is sound produced and how do we
perceive sound by sound by what
mechanism do we perceive sound
if you understand that then we'll be
able to answer this question yeah so
let's unpack a little bit what is sound
sound
is vibration
vibration vibration of what
the vibration of the air molecules in
the atmosphere
that's what sound is so i have a sound
source this the larynx
my sound box voice box yeah over here
it's producing the speech that i am
currently
uh
issuing forth yeah
and
that is what that does is it produces
vibrations and that these vibrations
make the
air molecules in this room
vibrate
to vibrate at those frequencies that we
perceive as sound
so these air molecules vibrate
and those vibrations are picked up by
our ears there's this very sensitive
structure called the eardrum and there's
a whole structure that goes that
connects the eardrum
to
nerve nerve endings that essentially go
back into the brain and that's how we
perceive these vibrations as sound so
our brain interprets these vibrations at
various frequencies it's sounds of
different pitches
high pitch sound low pitch sound that
sort of thing right
all right
so that that's how it works so different
frequencies produ we interpret that as
different pitches of sound now i am
speaking in this room in a certain
location on the planet you all may be on
different parts of the planet maybe an
opposite side of the planet depending on
where you are and you are able to hear
me what's happening i have this
instrument here it's called the
microphone it turns it it interprets
these vibrations that i'm producing in
terms of
i think the electromagnetic spectrum
that is then transmitted across the
internet and then it is
it is reinterpreted again back as
regular sound through whatever speaker
you have whether it is these these tiny
little speakers right tiny little
speakers or big speakers or whatever so
that's how it happens
so sound
is the vibration
of a medium the medium we are in is the
earth's atmosphere the air molecules
that we uh
are immersed in
sound is the vibration of that and there
are various there's a whole frequency of
sound waves as well like just like we
have
a spectrum electromagnetic spectrum
there's a sound spectrum as well we
can't hear
uh what is it called what the bats here
uh
ultrasound it's called ultrasound right
cats and dogs can hear that i believe
there are certain vessels that only dogs
can hear you blow it you won't hear a
thing but dogs will be like what is that
here i am
right so the human
ear can perceive a certain range of
frequencies of sound
now that we kind of understand what
sound is vibration of the air molecules
around us
the question is is it possible to hear
sound from a black hole
now black holes are way way far away
from here the closest black hole that we
know of is the
ultra it's a super massive black hole at
the center of our galaxy
and this is a reasonably passive black
hole it doesn't have an accretion disk
so it's not doing much yeah
and it is sitting
in vacuum
i think there is an internet issue is
there
let me resolve that hopefully
the connection is unstable it says one
second please give me a minute
i think there is an issue with the
connection
happens
occasionally
um
let me take a look at the chat are you
able to see me well
is there a lag
is there a lag is it fine is the
correction good i think the connection
is good now okay thank you very much for
the feedback
let's go back to the question okay so
now that we know what sound is
sound is
the vibration of the air molecules
around us that's what we perceive as
sound
a black hole sits in outer space
there is no atmosphere there there are
no air molecules there it's an almost
perfect vacuum
so if a black hole
a
vibrates in some way or whatever yeah it
would vibrate in the gravitational fl
gravitational waves range yeah
it will have gravitational frequencies
so there is no air molecules or
atmosphere that it is making vibrate
so then how do we hear sound from a
black hole you can't
but what you can do
is when there's a merger
let's say two black holes are merging
they merge together they're gonna
make big waves in the fabric of
space-time
they're gonna create these gravitational
waves massive gravitational waves see
when you look when you when you're
sitting at the seashore
hopefully you see little small waves
little ripples yeah
but unfortunately once in a
long time once in a few decades you have
a tsunami
a tsunami is just a wave but it's a
massive wave
so when you have two black holes merging
they produce a gravitational wave
tsunami a massive wave with a huge
amplitude and that's what our
gravitational wave detectors pick up
now these gravitational waves have
frequencies and wavelengths
just like light has frequencies in
wavelength and just like sound has
frequency of the wavelength so what
scientists can do is they can
once they have detected a gravitational
wave signal they can interpret that
frequency
in terms of sound waves and they could
produce an equivalent sound
that is representative of the
gravitational wave that was produced by
the by the merger of two black holes
so you can interpret that extrapolate
that into the sound spectrum and take a
look at what it would sound like if it
was not gravitational waves but sound
waves that's what you can do
then you also have certain black holes
that are surrounded by these massive
massive gas clouds accretion disks
in these tightly packed dense gas clouds
there are molecules of gas
over there if you are unlucky enough to
be there you would hear sound if you are
in that environment yeah so if you are
there you could actually hear sound and
if you can detect that uh accretion disk
and for whatever whatever means you can
see at what frequency is vibrating you
can recreate that sound on earth and
that would be actual sound yeah so these
are some of the ways in which you can
possibly hear sound from black hole
firstly you could interpret the
gravitational waves it's emitting in
terms of
auditory sound waves and that's what
that would sound like or if it actually
has an accretion disk and that accretion
disk is vibrating at a certain frequency
you could recreate that frequency here
on our planet and you could hear what it
actually sounds like over there
so these are two possible ways in which
you could hear sound from a black hole
you would have to recreate it over here
you cannot directly hear it because it's
separated from us by the immense vacuum
of space but you can recreate and
reinterpret that sound on earth and it
would sound like what it sounds like
over there
to some extent
all right
okay yatarta says are black holes
actually fuzz balls fuzz balls what are
fuzz balls i you know what i like about
this question
the first part of the question is are
black holes actually first balls and
then he asks what are first balls that's
how you do science you keep on asking
why or what until you get to the root of
the matter
right
so first of all to understand whether
black holes are first balls or not we
have to understand what first balls are
okay so what are first balls i think it
was samir martha who came up with the
term first ball if i'm not mistaken
that's the
paper about 15 20 years ago that he
published
first balls so what are these fuzz balls
a first ball is a bag of strings
or
bag box
ball a ball
a ball that contains strings a ball
filled with strings now you should ask
me the question if you are awake
what are strings
you want to get to the root of the
matter you ask the question what are
strings i am saying a first ball is a
ball a bag of strings so then you need
to know what strings are
strings
are one dimensional
vibrating objects made up of pure energy
essentially you can think of it that way
that's the
best analogy i could offer you
one-dimensional
uh
objects made of pure energy that are
vibrating in various manners
now now you could also ask me what
dimensions are let's not go as far as
deep as that i i'm sure we all
understand what dimensions are three
dimensions of space that we live in
length breadth height
three dimension this is a
three-dimensional object yeah it has
length height height and breadth and so
on and there's a fourth dimension of
time which we perceive vaguely and so on
so
these strings
are not three-dimensional objects
they're not two-dimensional objects flat
they are one-dimensional objects made of
pure energy energy that vibrates at
certain frequencies in complex ways and
that's that is the building block of
string theory yeah
so
so there is this is one way in which you
can actually create a black from the
inside out you can build a black hole
mathematically from the inside out using
one dimensional strings you put a bunch
of strings together in a ball
and then you calculate the properties
this ball has and you can build a black
hole out of that so how are black holes
built mathematically they typically
emerge as the solutions of einstein's
field equations in general relativity
even before general relativity came out
in 1915 the the concept of black hole
black holes did exist yeah
it all starts with the concept of escape
velocity every object has a certain
escape velocity for earth it's what 11
12 kilometers per second one one quote
me on that somewhere around that the sun
has a much higher escape velocity
jupiter is a much higher velocity so for
each
gravitating object you have a certain
escape velocity
what if an object is so dense and so
large
so dense
that the escape velocity is equal to or
greater than the speed of light in in
that case even light cannot escape from
that object and that is the concept of
the black hole so it's something that
that predates general relativity but the
actual rigorous mathematical
singularities emerged out of the
equations of general relativity
solutions of einstein's field equations
which gave us black hole solutions
singularities singularities are these
horrific scary objects
that divide you by zero
all right
unphysical objects which actually tells
us that there is something deeper at
work over here and there are certain
flaws in general relativity which can
only be solved by quantizing it when we
still haven't been able to do that so
typically black holes are they arise out
of the equations of general relativity
general relativity is a large scale
theory macroscopic theory a theory of
the macroscopic world now when you are
building
a black hole
in a quantum manner you have to do it
inside out instead of outside in
so how do you build a black hole
quantum quantumly quantumly there are
multiple ways of doing it you can
model a black hole as a bag of photons
you could do that it works
it gives you a whole different set of
properties than the
classical black holes yeah the short
shield radius doesn't work there there's
something called the critical radius
which is different from the social
radius and so on i'll not go there
so what samir mathur as far as i know
he's the first person if i'm not if i'm
mistaken forgive me but what samir
martha did was he
created a mathematical black hole out of
a collection of strings
and he called this thing a fuzz ball
right
so that's how that's one way of building
a black hole inside out at the very
small from the very small scale using
one dimensional strings you could use a
bag of photons a black or a bag of
gravitons or whatever you could do it in
a variety of ways so what
this model is is the first ball model a
bag of strings and you can
you know solve the mathematical problem
you can work out the equations and that
gives you a black hole yeah
and that kind of solves the
not solved but it's it's one way of
avoiding the singularity problem
the singularity problem is that deep
inside the black hole at the very center
uh the space-time curvature becomes
infinite and the density of matter also
becomes infinite which is unphysical
infinities are unphysical so in the case
of the first ball model you have a bag
of strings so there is no there is no
singularity within interesting isn't it
so that's what the first ball model is
our black house first balls i don't know
i don't know nobody knows nobody knows
what black holes actually are
we will know only when we have a black
hole in our lab and we can you know poke
and prod it and do various things to it
so we don't have a black hole in the lab
we have objects that appear to be black
holes that we have observed here
supermassive black holes they could even
be wormholes who knows they could even
be white holes who knows right so we
don't know for sure what they are but
they do appear to be black holes they do
exhibit all the properties that a black
hole would have but we still don't know
what exactly there are you could you
could create objects mathematically
quantum mechanically that are not quite
black holes but almost black holes
and they would behave almost the same
from a far distance you could not be
able to tell what they are you know
so
so the the answer is we don't know what
black holes actually are because
we know what happens when you are
falling towards a black hole we know
there is an event horizon we know that
when you cross the event horizon horizon
you are lost to the universe more or
less and what happens inside we don't
know no one knows exactly what inside
what is inside is there this monstrous
singularity is there a bag is is there a
bag of strings is it a bag of photons is
it a bag of gravitons is it something
else unicorns and ice cream we don't
know right
and that's
what the research is all about that's
what we are trying to investigate what
actually are black holes what would be
inside a black hole right
and to do that to to actually figure out
eventually what is inside a black hole
we will have to crack the puzzle of
quantum gravity we will have to
reconcile einstein's general relativity
with quantum mechanics and quantum field
theory it's not been possible to do that
thus far people have tried that's why
string theory was was devised as a
possible solution but it has its own set
of problems it doesn't seem to be giving
us answers so we still don't know what
what's going on
so
so that's what a first ball is that's
what the first ball model is that's what
and we still don't know what actually
black holes consist of
what's inside a black hole so the the
answer is i don't know no one knows no
you ask any physicist they will say we
don't know but we have these different
approaches we have these different
possibilities different models but which
of these works which of this is the
correct model we still don't know as of
2022. that's where we are but good
question very interesting and
fascinating
topic
laksha sharma says could this mysterious
dark matter just be primordial black
holes all along
remove their black holes so what are
they okay first of all what's dark
matter the universe has a certain amount
of mass
we observe the universe through our eyes
through telescopes through various
instruments etc and we see all these
stars and we see galaxies and we see gas
clouds and dust clouds and nebulae and
things like that
every single god damn thing we see in
the universe
is less than five percent of the actual
mass of the universe
ninety-five percent of the mass of the
universe roughly
is dark
we don't know what it is everything we
see is less than five percent of the
universe
that's how little we know about the
universe so 95 percent is unknown to us
out of this 95
roughly 25 roughly roughly very roughly
is dark matter which we have some idea
what would what properties it has and
all that and the rest is dark energy
which we have no clue about
a dark energy seems to be some kind of
force or some kind of fluid that
permeates the universe it's here right
now
right here right now yeah but
we don't know what it is and it seems to
be an anti-gravity kind of force it's
it's
it's making the universe expand it's and
the expansion of the universe is
accelerating
so it's it's actually
making space time itself expand yeah
that's what dark energy is dark matter
is this missing matter this dark matter
that
we know it exists
it makes galaxies rotate in a certain
way which is counter to what they would
rotate like
if it was only the visible matter right
so typically
every typically most galaxies have a
dark matter hello
a spherical dark matter hello a typical
galaxy is a disc yeah like the milky way
like the andromeda galaxy it's enveloped
in a massive dark matter hello which is
actually
about 90 percent of the galaxy's mass
typically a galaxy whatever you see all
the luminous matter stars although all
that is about 10 of the galaxy's mass
and about 90 is a dark matter halo
typically typically on average roughly
yeah
so that's what dark matter is now the
question is what is dark matter what is
it composed of what we know is that
it doesn't interact electromagnetically
which means we can't see it it's
invisible
it's not dark it's invisible
so it doesn't interact
electromagnetically it has no
electromagnetic interaction most likely
it only interacts through the
gravitational force
so it is some kind of exotic for us
exotic matter because it's not something
we experience
in in day-to-day life
there is most likely dark matter passing
through the earth
the solar system
may be enveloped in dark matter there
could be a wind of dark matter particles
passing through me right now
yeah
and we will not know about it so it is
some mysterious matter some a mysterious
particle or a mysterious class of
particles that all seem to have this
common property that they interact only
gravitationally uh some people tried to
postulate that there could be weak
interaction as well the weak nuclear the
weak force
and that's where the axion came from and
all that but
and then
various other things as well it's not
quite worked out so the most
likely hypothesis is cold dark matter
made up of purely gravitating particles
so what are these gravitating particles
we still don't know so
could it be primordial black holes now
let's ask ourselves what are these
primordial black holes when we think of
black holes we think of these monstrous
objects at the center of galaxies that
are sucking everything in yeah
but um black holes aren't that nasty or
evil typically they're just gravitating
objects purely gravitating objects now
they could have charge also and magnetic
fields but yeah
so what are primordial black holes so in
the very very very incredibly very early
universe
uh
these we know the the big bang model
yeah at the very beginning of space of
time
all the mass and energy and everything
that we see in the universe and
everything we don't see was concentrated
in a single point
an infinite infinitesimally dense and
hot point and then something made that
expand that is the expansion of
space-time and that's what we call the
big bang it was not an explosion it was
an expansion of space time and
everything contained within it
so in the very early universe you could
have had these quantum fluctuations that
arise out of heisenberg's uncertainty
principle quantum field theory all that
so these quantum fluctuations happen we
know they exist
they happen everywhere
empty space the vacuum of space is not
empty it's teeming with this virtual
particle anti-particle pairs
quantum fluctuations so in the very
early universe quantum fluctuations
could have produced regions of over
density
densities that could have been the seeds
of black holes very tiny microscopic
black holes primordial black holes in
the primordial very early universe and
there could have been uh and a massive
amount of primordial black holes produce
a different
early
epochs in the universe's history
uh preheating re-heating even
pre-inflation maybe post-inflation also
yeah there are various mechanisms
through which there could be there could
have been an overproduction of primary
primordial black holes so most likely
primordial black holes were produced in
enormous abundant quantities in the very
early universe small microscopic black
holes yes
the question is where are they
where are they now we know that black
holes have a temperature that
thermodynamic objects if you have a
temperature you're going to give off
radiation and the smaller a black hole
is the hotter it is the bigger it is the
colder it is so supermassive black holes
are very cold very very very cold they
could be colder than the the temperature
of space the cosmic microwave background
radiation temperature
but the smaller black hole is the hotter
it is and the hotter it is the more it
the faster it essentially gives off
radiation the faster it evaporates and
the end point of a black hole's life is
a massive explosion boom that's how it
goes that's how it dies yeah
so if primordial black holes were
produced in enormous quantities in the
early universe and they were very small
they could have possibly all exploded
and died out evaporated out that's one
scenario the other scenario is that by
some unknown mechanism they still
survive until today
maybe uh
they they they leave plank scale
remnants the so-called plank ons
cornucopians whatever they call them
these days
uh planck scale objects and maybe at the
planck scale there is no more
evaporation of black holes in which case
you could have a massive quantity of
planck scale
black holes that
are wandering around and maybe they make
up
what we call dark matter
maybe through some mechanism we don't
understand
primordial black holes or micro black
holes could have formed bound states
quantum mount states and maybe in these
quantum bound states they don't
evaporate
and maybe these quantum bound states
don't behave like black holes but they
behave like exactly like cold dark
matter
super massive
not supermassive dark matter but but the
cold dark matter heavy particles there
are all these possibilities these
particles would be quite massive but
very very very small
and this is what
this is a theory that i have i had
co-authored in 2002 all the way back in
2002 you know
uh stable bounce days of primordial
black holes that could
uh
constitute
dark matter so these are all
possibilities there are there's no way
as of today of proving it if there are
bound states of primordial black holes
that are stable and they do exist they
would give off gravitational radiation
they would give up gravitational waves
quantized gravitational radiation but
this gravitation these gravitational
waves at the emit are not detectable
with the detectors that we have today
the best the only gravitational wave
detectors that work today are the ligo
detectors right
the ligo detectors can only detect
gravitational wave tsunamis enormous
gravitational waves not tiny ripples in
space time for that you need
extraordinarily sensitive detectors
which you don't have which you don't
have today so if primordial black holes
did form bound states and the quantum
quantized bound states those quantized
bowed states would give off quantized
gravitational radiation just like you
see light
that sort of thing in those frequencies
in similar frequencies but in the
gravitational wave domain yeah
but as of there's no way of proving it
so it's just a theory so it is possible
yes it is possible that
primordial black holes could be dark
matter or bound states of primordial
black holes could be dark matter or
planck scale remnants of primordial
black holes could be dark matter a
signal i would say it's a very high
possibility a strong possibility now
physicists have been looking for all
kinds of different
dark matter candidates there used to be
machos there used to be vimps
they were looking for uh they were
looking for gravitational wave micro
lensing the the macho thing yeah
massive compact hello objects machos
they they're looking for axions they're
looking for supersymmetric dark matter
all of these searches have turned up
empty-handed
maybe it's time to take primordial black
holes a little more seriously again
so it's it's an ongoing process but yes
i personally think primordial black
holes are a very important
candidate for dark matter
okay dr district says
why
do asian elephants have smaller tusks or
no tusks compared to their african
counterparts
uh i believe that asian elephants are
even physically somewhat smaller than
their african counterparts african
elephants typically i believe
grow larger somewhat larger than asian
elephants
and i believe even the african lions are
somewhat physically larger than asian
asiatic lions and the only asian lions
left are in india
western india gujarat the gear forest
region yeah
uh so why is it so well they have
evolved differently
they've evolved differently uh
africa and asia were connected let's
let's take a look at the map obviously
let's let's make sense to look at the
map since we are talking about these
things
where is our map
so
here's the map
so africa and asia were connected in
this region the sinai peninsula the
egypt
uh
egypt and
this region it's connected
so in the past uh animals could have
migrated around this place they had the
so-called barbary lion that lived on
both sides of the divide now you have
this artificial divide called the swiss
canal
it's it's an artificial thing it's not
it's not a natural thing so there used
to be this land connection here in the
past during the ice ages etc it would
have been possible to cross over through
the bab al-mandeb strait
and various other places as well
so there have been connections between
africa and asia so it's possible that
species transmigrated etc
but
so we have certain species that are
present on both continents lions are a
good example
elephants are another good example
now what we don't realize is how large
africa is
let's see africa asia comparison
is africa
size comparison
let's
take a look at that let me put this off
the screen
and let's put something else on the
screen
africa asia size comparison now why am i
comparing sizes
because it's relevant
see how large africa is
see where india fits into africa can you
see this is india this is china
this is the uk as big as madagascar the
us
africa is enormous and the maps that we
use the mercantile projection they don't
show us how large africa actually is
africa is a massive massive place
it's the the biggest continent of all
so
when you have animals that live in a
continent of this scale
they have massive amounts of territory
that they can
use as their
home range yeah massive territories they
will cover massive distances in various
migrations
and that has an effect over the
millennia on the size of an animal
an animal that has access to more
land
and more resources that sort of animal
can evolve can can afford
evolutionary
from an evolutionary standpoint to glu
to grow larger because there is an
abundance of territory it can cover in
an abundance of food that it has
africa's grasslands savannahs etc are
abundant in food in in grassland and and
all that
so
in today we have very few wild animals
left in africa even in the 1960s 1970s
you had so many more wild animals zebras
gazelles elephants it's all been killed
off by the white people by the europeans
who
who used africa as a place for their
hunting activities and just killing
animals for for sport and
you know just just
wanton massacres pointless massacres of
animals that's why the numbers have come
down so badly there are very few animals
left in africa today africa was this
enormous continent
filled with
herds
incredibly large herds of animals
yeah
and it could support
so many animals that's how rich africa
is has been
so these animals they had access to such
an incredible abundance of resources
that's why they typically grew larger
that's why the african lions are
typically larger than asiatic lions and
that's why african elephants
have over the millennia thousands of
years tens of thousands of years evolved
differently from their counterparts
their cousins who live in asia in asia
the terrain is different from that of
africa
asia is full of these river valleys
let's take a look at the indian
subcontinent there are mountain ranges
the aravalis the sahyadris the vindhyas
the himalayas et cetera
the the the western ghats and so on so
forth you have that
and you have forest today we don't have
forests in the past you had these
massive forests
and river valleys
in africa you do not have forests you
have these savannas grasslands yeah
so that's why
the the terrain
in the living environment is different
in asia compared to africa and that's
why it has caused these species to
evolve in different ways when it comes
to asia and africa so because of that
the african elephants typically grew
larger and they had longer tasks when
you grow larger your test also become
longer
that's typically
how evolution goes
you adapt based on your environment
so that's why
asian elements elephants are smaller and
they have smaller tasks compared to the
african counterparts
okay swapnil says is it possible to
print bones using a three-dimensional 3d
printer to replace bones that have been
broken or damaged beyond repair and
human or animal body
yes 3d printing technology is is really
uh coming up it's it's uh it's something
that that is possibly poised to
transform the way we do things yeah the
way we construct things the way we build
material build things maybe it's
something that could transform medicine
as well
so when someone's bone is broken when
someone shatters their femur or tibia or
radius or ulna or whatever
if the if the
if the break is very clean you can just
set the bone again and immobilize it for
like a few months three months or so
three four months whatever depending on
the person you take calcium tablets and
it heals you know in in a few months
but if the
if the break is complex
if if the bone is shattered into pieces
or something then typically what you do
is you insert a metal metal rod rod a
steel rod a sterile steel rod
and you
and you uh
you reconstruct
the bone
you may
piece it together using screws yeah
that's what's done
and that's typically what's been done
thus far
and you have to make sure that the
materials you use are sterile and they
are non-reactive
biologically right so typically
people have used steel stainless steel
sterile stainless steel well treated
they have used
this also been the use of ceramics so
ceramics are also very non-reactive they
and and they are well suited for this
sort of
uh purpose
so in the future yes it's certainly
possible
that uh
3d printed bones could be used so
someone let's say they've shattered some
some power some bone
you could remove those shattered pieces
and insert
an exact replica of the of how the bone
used to be
but 3d printed
so it's all it's certainly going to be
possible i'm even hearing that you could
have 3d printed organs in the future
yeah
i think that's still some time off
that's still a few years of maybe a
couple of decades off perhaps
but yes
we are witnessing these advances in
medical technology so
the question is what sort of material is
going to be used to 3d print the bones
um
i would say it should be something
that's similar to the bone to what what
constitutes a bone itself see bones are
complex
complex things
a bone is not just a a solid object it
is porous you know
it is biologically active it is alive
inside a bone there is a there is this
hollow space in which you have bone
marrow bone marrow is what generates our
red blood cells in our blood yeah so the
bone marrow is very important
so
so um
if you replace
a damaged or destroyed bone with a 3d
printed bone obviously you will not be
able to recreate that but
one would
expect that you would use calcium based
material that would in a way recreate
what the
material or composition of the original
bone was like so i think it's going to
be possible i i don't think it's been
done thus far but i don't think it's too
far away so yes in the future you will
certainly have these things happening
more and more materials including
biological materials and bones
will be 3d printed
and that could certainly be
the future of medicine yeah so i think
it's going to happen soon enough it's if
it's not already been done
okay harsh says is human extinction
possible if no then why if it is
possible then by which way
virus outbreak ai takeover
human calamities natural calamities
human wars space problem
um
see if you look at any species
it if you see our planet is about four
and a half billion
years old
and there have been various mass
extinctions on the planet
the most recent one was the
um what's it called
the chichalub event right the czech
impact which was something that happened
66 million years ago in which most of
the dinosaurs died out all the non-avian
dinosaurs died out
um
and various species over time have gone
extinct
but some survive we survive
and
our ancestors date back to the very
beginning
of the planet
so life is believed to have emerged the
most the unambiguous evidence is that
life emerged on our planet about 3.77
billion years before today yeah
those were very
primitive microorganisms as far as we
know and then over time more complex
biology emerged
evolved
you had microorganisms unicellular
organisms in the beginning then you had
different kinds of biology then you had
multicellular organisms and then more
complex life forms emerged then you had
various marine life
of a whole variety of marine life and
eventually these some of these marine
life forms emerged out
on to land
they developed the ability to breathe
the atmosphere and and use that force
for for staying alive and that's how you
had ground-based life forms and we are
somehow we are an example of that
so our ancestors would most likely date
back to the very beginning 3.77 billion
years ago
and we carry dna
which
which most likely dates back to the
beginning of life on our planet
so we have survived so our survival
some people would say that that homo
sapiens is about
300 000 years old only well homo sapiens
had predecessors and ancestors
right
archaic humans
and those archaic humans had older
ancestors which were the the first apes
around 20 million years before today and
those apes had ancestors the the
mammal-like creatures that survived the
chick-fil-a impact 66 million years ago
those little rat like creatures those
rat-like creatures had ancestors that
were the fish
that lived
in the marine environment of the planet
billions of years ago those fish had
unicellular ancestors so we have
survived
close to four billion years yeah so we
are a very hardy species it's very hard
to kill us off we have survived all
kinds of mass extinctions yes we have
but of course human extinction is
possible
and we have made it actually quite
quite possible to to destroy everything
off
if two nations go to war and they are
both nuclear powers who knows what could
happen it could kill off most of
humanity
uh
you could have environmental
catastrophes human created environmental
catastrophes if we destroy all our
forests
animals will die off if animals die off
then you're going to have a whole change
in the atm in the in the ecosystem
environment we could lose our food
sources even our plant sources of food
and that could kill us off that could
cause mass famines and starvation and
whatnot and very few humans could
survive maybe all humans could could die
off if there is a chickula like kind of
event you know a comet or asteroid that
impacts the earth and we are not able to
prevent that from happening that could
most likely kill us off
so lots of scenarios are possible virus
outbreak yeah you could have a pandemic
a pandemic of some kind an epidemic of
some kind
we have had such things in the past in
the past more than half of europe's
population was decimated by the black
death the plague which kind of skipped
india for some reasons
but it ruined the rest of the world so
yes you could have
viruses you could have pandemics
natural or not
you could have wars nuclear war is a
great way of killing off everything on
the planet not everything life will
survive but we we could
end up becoming extinct space problem
like you're mentioning is is the impact
of an asteroid or comet which
will certainly happen in the future it
could happen in the next 50 million
years it could happen next week we don't
know yeah
uh i think nasa keeps an eye on on all
the near earth objects especially
objects of particular concern which
which kind of tend to cross earth's
orbit around the sun intersect with it
uh thus far there is no immediate cause
of concern when it comes to these
objects but yeah
there could be objects that we not we
are not aware of you know it just takes
one to kill you off so so yes and in ai
takeover
that's also a non-zero
possibility
a non-zero probability of that happening
so it it doesn't necessarily have to be
a fully conscious sentient ai it could
be just
a non-sentient ai that can still take
over the world and possibly kill off
humanity it is possible so i think there
are
multiple ways in which humanity can
or could
become extinct and we need to all work
together and ensure these things don't
happen yeah
so it is certainly possible it is
certainly possible it's always been
possible in the past it's it's even more
possible because of our own doing today
and and for that we need good leadership
and we need to take humanity in the
right direction
uh right now things are not going well
we are
we are damaging
the environment we are destroying the
oceans
if it continues like this the oceans
will be choked choked with plastic you
could have mass extinctions of fish
there's already overfishing that's
happening on the routine basis so yeah
this is not good
if we keep on going this way it's gonna
it could it can lead to a catastrophe
so yeah it's gonna take some good
leadership
in the future for us to uh keep going in
the right direction so i think human
human extinction is certainly possible
in in a multiple
in a multiplicity of ways and hopefully
we we ensure it doesn't happen
jab live says why are there no flying
cars yes why are there no flying cars i
would like to have one i will pay
whatever it takes you know
if i don't have money i will borrow
money
i would love to have a flying car but
the fact is we don't have flying cars
why is it so
we do have certain uh drone kind of
things like you know um
human carrying don't we have a human
carrying drone
uh let's see if that is possible let me
put that on the screen where's the
screen here's the screen here we are so
we have these drone vehicles
that can carry humans we even have that
uh
that surfboard kind of thing that that
that takes you in the air
you know
not sure what is called wind boarding or
whatever so you have these vehicles
there are essentially like you know
drones but those that can carry a human
being
enough for one person you can even have
multiple people in there so this is
essentially a flying car
we already have it
we already have it so but why has it not
been adopted
widely
now the technology exists but it's not
adopted widely yet why is it so
think about it like this
let's say
somebody a teenager is given
a flying car
now teenagers are kind of not very
mature people with good reason because
they still don't have enough experience
of the world and teenagers like to party
do do various things you know alcohol
and stuff let's say you have a teenager
who is drunk in a flying car
what could happen
when you have
road vehicles they are essentially
traveling on a two-dimensional surface
yes they can go back and forth east or
west that sort of thing
they are traveling on a flat surface and
they are traveling on pre-designated
roads
so if there is any collision any
accident it will only happen in that
particular place
when you give them access to
three-dimensional space which means they
can also go up and up and down
then
it's almost impossible to regulate
their behavior they could go in any
direction they could crash into any
building
that's way more hazardous
and then they can even they could even
crash into airplanes and things like
that
so these are the reasons why
uh
it's not really taken out taken off this
technology the technology already exists
it may be expensive this thing these
these flying cars they cost i don't know
ten thousand dollars maybe hundred
thousand dollars i'm not sure how much
it'll cost i'm sure people can afford it
but there will be a huge amount of
regulation there's already a lot of
regulation on these small drones there
are various people who use drones for
for videography and photography they um
when someone is photo when someone is
taking a video of a wedding
you typically have a drone shot yeah all
the people celebrating from the sky then
you have various filmmakers who use
drones various youtubers who use drones
to give a cinematic image cinematic
imagery and all that but
we're already witnessing a significant
amount of
regulation on who can acquire drones and
in what way they can use them they need
all kinds of permissions they need a
license there are certain places where
you're not allowed to use your drone and
every time you have a drone flight you
need to first take permission from the
authorities that on so-and-so date and
so-and-so place location i will have a
drone flight for so-and-so duration it
will go this high and so on so forth it
is important that this is done otherwise
you're going to have drones flying
everywhere crashing into all kinds of
things taking down airplanes commercial
airplanes and whatnot is dangerous
and the same thing applies to flying
cars once you start allowing people to
fly around it's gonna be chaos
it's gonna be chaos
so that's why i don't see it taking off
to a significant extent extent anytime
in the future because it's dangerous and
many people are irresponsible you can be
responsible on a two-dimensional surface
when you are irresponsible in three
dimensions the damage you can do is is
much more
massive
yeah
so these are the reasons why thus far is
not taken off in the future there could
be
some people allowed to use these drones
and flying cars but again it will be
very very strictly and strongly
regulated with good reason so that's why
we don't have flying cars thus far
india is going to launch a one billion
dollar quantum mission to expand india's
capabilities in quantum computing
national research foundation nrf scheme
will be ready in six months which will
take care of the funding of universities
and research centers your views on this
you know it is good it is great it's
very encouraging that the government is
investing money
in quantum computing we need to get
involved in this
india cannot be of cannot afford to be
left behind
in the quantum computing race in any
other race any technological race
it's very good it's very encouraging
that we are spending one billion dollars
which is not a small amount of money
it's good
the question is how is the money going
to be used that's all that's always the
question
i can throw money at something but how
is the money gonna be used that's always
the real problem
now india's universities you gotta fund
them
is there any research happening in
india's universities do india's
universities have the research
capabilities
maybe
this money will be used to develop
the capability to do research the other
question is do india's academicians
have the ability to do research
to answer the question you to see how
people
are given jobs and how they are promoted
in india's universities you
unfortunately have the reservation
system which means it is not a
merit-based system
you look at india's professors
academicians 95 of them are not capable
of doing research they have no
inclination or interest in doing
research we know that
there are some good scientists no doubt
there are some really good scientists as
well maybe one percent
no doubt but 95 of them are
unfortunately mediocrities
they're not capable of doing research
they don't have the understanding of
what research is
how will they take india forward in this
i what i would like what i hope happens
is that we set up new institutions
where this research is done not the good
old universities that have been around
for 3000 years not 3000 sorry these all
of india's universities are
the old ones
i will not name any but these are
colonial institutions
they are run in the same old colonial
bureaucratic fashion
the money the budget is always
controlled by the bureaucrats but the
non-teaching staff and the teaching
staff itself is doesn't have any
inclination for doing research
how much research is coming out of india
answer me
how much research has come out genuine
how much genuine valuable path-breaking
research has come out of india in the
past 20 years in the field of the
sciences give me some examples can you
come up with anything that's the problem
that's a problem there are good
scientists some good scientists no doubt
but they are shackled by the system
so you throw money at the you you invest
money in these universities i wonder
where the money will be used
you go to certain very very high ranking
institutions in this in this country in
india
you will find that the labs
have 20 30 year old equipment but the
conference rooms and the washrooms
have millions of dollars invested in
them that's what you find that's one
that's what happens when bureaucrats
take decisions and they decide where to
put money
yeah
so that is the problem so you have the
same system that's going on you put more
money into the same system you will get
more of the same results
you understand
so what india needs is first of all we
need to reform the education system the
universities must be made more research
oriented and this promotions and hiring
should be done based on merit only
not based on quotas and reservations and
affirmative action and god knows what
else
that's how you take the country
backwards not forwards
look at how germany transformed itself
in the late 19th century
it became a technological and scientific
superpower almost overnight
they had these universities based purely
on merit
huge amounts of money were invested in
real research cutting edge research
and the scientists were hired based on
their capabilities their ability and the
merit and they were promoted based on
merit
all the various german scientists who
were at the forefront of the quantum
revolution
they became full professors when they
were in their 20s
some of them became heads of department
or heads of institutions in their early
30s
lots of names you know heisenberg's
holding einstein so many so many more
born
even other countries like niels bohr
sweden sweden was it sweden most likely
and so on there's so many that's how you
take a nation forward scientifically and
technologically you have the same old
corrupt colonial system
you can
pour in 100 billion dollars it's going
to produce the same results so that's
the problem
so if if india is spending a billion
dollars in quantum computing i hope we
create new institutions new institutes
that are purely research based
and where they will hire people based on
their ability not based on quotas
and the only
way the money is used will be
in doing research
not in
the salaries of non-teaching staff and
bureaucrats and and
million dollar washrooms and trillion
dollar conference rooms not that that's
a complete waste of money look at drdo
drdo has roughly 30 000 employees out of
those 30 000 employees
about 5000 are scientists
25 000 employees are non-scientists
non-scientific staff what kind of a joke
is this this is how the nation's money
is being wasted
so
it's a good thing the government wants
to invest a billion dollars in quantum
computing
the question is how is the money going
to be used and that's where i have a few
questions
just saying it
all right
okay the question is uh captain burp 91
what is thrust vectoring which is used
in modern day fighter jets like sukhoi
su-30mki lockheed martin f22 raptor and
how does the radar on f s 400 detect
stealth jets but a conventional radar
cannot thank you
okay what is thrust vectoring it's very
simple see uh let me show you what mac
diamonds are
mac diamonds
okay there's something called mac
diamonds this is the exhaust of of
jet engine shock diamonds mac diamonds
call it whatever you want
so typically you have a
jet engine
that has an exhaust that goes
in the opposite direction of which the
jet engine itself goes it goes right
now in thrust vectoring what you can do
is you can
control the direction in which the
exhaust goes so let me show you thrust
vectoring
first vector ring so it's a technology
you see this
you can
send the jet in if you have two engines
you can make the exhaust of the two
engines go in different directions in
using that you get more control
on the way the jet on on the way the
fighter plane
can be maneuvered
so thrust vectoring fighter planes which
have the thrust vectoring capabilities
are
more maneuver maneuverable than a jet
engine than a jet fighter jet plane that
does not have a thrust vectoring ability
so what a thrust vectoring uh
what the technology does is that it
allows you to direct the exhaust
any in any direction in three dire in
three dimensions
so that gives you essentially hyper
maneuverability
can you see you can you can
send the exhaust in any direction
direction you want
so that essentially is is thrust
vectoring like you said the sukhoi
30 fighter plane the lockhead martin f
22 fighter plane and various other
fighter planes have this capability
that's what thrust vectoring is now how
does a radar on the s 400 system detect
stealth jets but a conventional radar
cannot
actually
all radars
can detect stealth jets
the question is at what range
that's the only question
a good
powerful radar
is one that can detect a stealth jet at
a large distance
a mediocre radar may be able to detect
it only at 10 kilometer range at which
you can't do anything
yeah because
a stealth jet typically flies
let's say you talk about the f-35 which
is a reasonably stealthy jet
it's uh it can fly supersonic
so if you can detect that of the plane
with your radar
at only 10 kilometers distance it's
gonna be gone in an eye blink of time
and then again you cannot track it so a
good radar is one that can detect a
stealth jet at a
longer distance at a greater
distance
uh so i think the uh
s 400 radar
if i am not mistaken can detect a
stealth jet like um
a typical stealth it at about 40 50
kilometers
distance
right
so that's not a very big distance you
get a plane can traverse that distance
very quickly but
what it can do is it can lock onto the
plane
and
so the s 400 radar is the
aesa radar active electronically scanned
whatever
radar which is a very difficult
technology to to master
so s 400 the system it has multiple
radar that is it has a network of radars
that all feed feed into a
three-dimensional battle space
environment that's what they create
and even the missiles have radars of
their own
so what the system does it it uses
inputs from multiple radar systems
to paint a unified
picture of the air space
and these are all aesa radars which can
detect stealth jets at about 40 50
kilometers distance so they use this to
track the the the aircraft
so it's able to track it it launches a
missile
and it keeps on talking to the missile
until the missile is at a range where
its own radar can detect the stealth jet
then the missile
is left to go on its own autonomously
so that's typically how it works
so all radars can actually detect
stealth jets the only thing is is
is the distance good enough you want to
detect the stealth jet as far away from
you as possible so that you have the
maximum possible reaction time and
decision making time
if you are able to detect it only for
three seconds you can't do much with
that
if you can detect it for like 30 seconds
you can do
something with that you know
so that's how it is so i think the s400
radar is good and it's able to detect
strength that's i think around 30 40 50
kilometers distance which is which gives
it a reasonable
amount of time to do some damage yeah
so yeah that's how it works
radar technology
tick curiosity says who
do you think that the internet is the
greatest and most influential invention
until date it's certainly one of the
most powerful
and most influential inventions uh it's
brought the whole world together
the internet became uh reasonably uh
well adopted i think in the late 1990s
people were using it in the mid 90s but
uh we had the dot-com bubble that that
in silicon valley in the late 90s then
those dot com crash and then
things went in a different direction and
the internet became
started becoming adopted for for uh
financial transactions for banking and
other things that's when it was taken
seriously
and now it's used for almost everything
you cannot imagine life without the
internet today so it is certainly it is
it's most likely the most
most influential invention and it
started as
a means of making computers talk to each
other over large distances you know
once that happened i think it started
with arpa net
in the us
maybe it was first tried out in cern in
geneva that's what they didn't possibly
i'm not sure i don't remember the exact
history but it started as a means of
making computers talk to each other
remotely over long distances once that
was feasible then they started creating
networks of computers who would talk to
each other and through which through
this network you could share documents
and data and over time
then what happened is that browsers
appeared internet browsers
through which you could appear through
which you could browse web pages coded
in html then you had css that you had
javascript and things were built on top
of each other
so it started as a very bare bones thing
and slowly various technologies were
built on top of that layers and layers
and layers of technology now we have
search engine you have entire
computational engines and whatnot
algorithms
uh some people say the internet could
have a mind of its own who knows yeah
so yeah i think it's
one of the if not the most
powerful and influential invention we
have ever seen it's completely
transformed
uh
humanity yeah the human experience human
existence so yeah most likely the most
powerful the greatest most influential
invention till date
okay ayush says what are gravitons are
they real
[Music]
uh
gravitons okay so let's talk about the
forces
we know of four forces in nature four
forces of nature
uh
the weak nuclear force the strong
nuclear force the electromagnetic force
and the gravitational force we have
these four forces now if you look at the
standard model we have these we have
what's called exchange particles what
are exchange particles these are
particles that are
exchanged in the exchange of these
particles
produces what we perceive as these
forces
uh
mediator particles exchange particles so
the exchange particle when it comes to
the stronger nuclear force is the gluon
the gluon
uh
then the exchange particle for the weak
nuclear force
is the w and the z bosons yeah
the exchange particle for the
electromagnetic force is the photon
photons are exchanged virtual virtual
photons
keeping in
keeping
within the parameters of the heisenberg
uncertain principle we have the exchange
of virtual particles virtual photons it
is this
exchange of virtual photons that gives
rise to what we perceive as
electromagnetism yeah
so we have electromagnetic attraction
repulsion depending on the charges and
all that and you have the extent of
photons that produces this force
similarly we have the force of gravity
now it is hypothesized or theorized that
there is an exchange particle that
mediates gravity as well which is the
hypothetical graviton yeah
so that's the fourth
exchange particle
that
is hypothesized it's never been detected
it's never been
uh
found
but it is hypothesized postulated
theorized to exist and
that could be behind the
force of gravity in case gravity is a
quantum force
in case gravity is a force at all
from the perspective of general
relativity gravity is not a force it is
simply the the warping the bending of
space time it is the bending of space
time that we perceive as gravity
yeah it is the bending and warping of
space time that
gives rise to what we feel is the force
of gravity now we know
that gravity is extremely weak it is the
weakest of the forces
how do we know this
how do we know this take a small magnet
small magnet the kind of magnet you put
in the fridge
yeah
that small magnet can pick up a paper
clip yes
it can people pick up a paper clip
do you understand what's happening
the magnet
it works
the force that a magnet uses it it
is the electromagnetic force right
so this little magnet is able to pick up
a paper clip
and
take it upwards
by doing that it is defeating the force
of gravity
now the magnet is this small
a magnet of this size is able to defeat
the force the gravitational force
exerted by an entire planet
the earth
so a tiny magnet
is it produces an electromagnetic force
that is stronger than the gravitational
force produced by the entire planet
earth
that illustrates
how weak a force gravity is
right so
the graviton is going to be incredibly
hard to detect you would need a planet
size detector even that would not work
well you even if you had a jupiter-sized
detector gravitational detector even
then it may be difficult to detect
gravitons so gravitons are
theoretical
uh particles
but uh detecting them is going to be uh
it's gonna be something we leave to our
descendants it's not gonna happen within
our lifetimes at all nobody's gonna even
try most likely to detect gravitons yeah
but that's what gravitons are are they
real we still don't know
if if the general relativity uh
picture is correct
then uh gravity may not be a quantum
force it might not be a force at all it
may just be an illusion that seems to be
a force it may just be the bending the
warping of space-time but if there is a
quantum theory of gravity
if gravity does emerge from the quantum
level from the from the quantum scale
then
you may have gravitons so we still don't
know but yes it is a hypothesized a
theorized theorized particle if you look
at any any illustration schematic of the
standard model particle zoo you will see
the gravity let's let's take a look at
the smart sun model
standard model particles
okay let's put that on the screen
standard model of particle physics
do we have the graviton in there
ah they have not included the graviton
as far as i can see
but yeah in some cases people do include
the graviton
so yeah it's it's something that's not
been detected yet thus far and that's
why some
in some cases you do include the
graviton in some cases you do not and so
on
so yeah that's the answer that's what
gravitons are are they real we still
don't know
maybe we'll know in the future someday
okay what is the temperature of space
the temperature of space is two point
something degrees kelvin
which is the temperature
of the electromagnetic radiation that
permeates space
and what is that electromagnetic
radiation it is the cosmic microwave
background radiation what is that it is
the after glow of the big bang
essentially that's what it is it is the
remnants of the first light
that's shown in the universe
right
now that light was once very
very hot very bright the temperature was
very high but then space
itself started expanding the expanding
universe
and slowly because of the expansion of
space-time
uh these these photons their wavelengths
got stretched out and now they're in the
far infrared very very very low energy
photons 2.7 or so kelvin
don't quote me two point something
kelvin very very cold very low energy
far infrared and that is essentially the
temperature of space two point something
kelvin which is close to zero kelvin
extremely cold that's what it is yeah
so that is the temperature of space
okay dr nishta says ayurvedic medicine
is mostly dismissed as being herbs
rubbish non-scientific by modern medical
practitioners what's your take on
experience on our way then why is modern
medicine having so much hostility
towards ayurvedic medicines
why is it even a special separate
medical branch despite having active
ingredients why is it not clubbed under
evidence-based medicine
it's not a scientific thing it's there
is a hostility towards indian culture in
indian traditions and that is why
ayurveda is dismissed but they then
use ayurvedic
knowledge but rebrand it
for instance you have something called
pranayam which is not ayurveda which is
indian tradition
we have something called pranayam
the west has rebranded it as cardiac
coherence breathing
it is nothing but pranayama but they are
rebranding it repackaging it under this
new name cardiac coherence breathing
and similarly in various ayurvedic
herbs like brahmi for example have been
rebranded as bacopa moneri or something
and there is research being done on
their active ingredients
it is being now uh
used as a so-called nootropic something
that can enhance your cognitive powers
and intelligence and brain power and all
that
there is research that's being done on
various ayurvedic
well-known herbs but they will all be
rebranded as something non-indian
so the
it is the hostility is not towards
ayurveda itself it's towards indian
culture
it's towards indian traditions
india is the oldest known civilization
india is the oldest continuously
existing civilization and the west
resents that
yeah
there's a whole different story to that
which we will not talk about over here
so it's not really being dismissed lots
of research i believe is happening but
it will not be
whenever some breakthrough happens
whenever they isolate the active
ingredient let's say curcumin
which is what is called haridra in
sanskrit
you know
it will be it will be rebranded as
something else and uh
most people will not even realize that
it's something that came out of ayurveda
so that's how it is so what needs to be
done india needs to create its own
scientific incidents of ayurvedic
research very simple
and whatever breakthroughs happen patent
them and make sure that they are
attributed to ayurveda whatever others
do
it's something we can't control and
that's something we should not complain
about why doesn't india start
its own research institutes
for ayurvedic research
you research the various ayurvedic herbs
and compounds etc
using 21st century scientific methods
isolate the actual active ingredients
and
patent that and commercialize it if
required
or make it available for free to people
whatever
so india needs to take steps
to safeguard its heritage the west is
under no obligation
to give india any any
see there is no justice in the world all
right people take what they can
so it's up to us
whether we want to allow people to take
everything that that we have created
uh so yeah that's how it is it is
certainly evidence-based medicine it is
certainly something that's been around
that's been proven to work for thousands
of years
it doesn't work in the allopathic manner
that you take this three these doses for
like five days and you're done
this is something that is part of a
lifestyle
but it does work
and if you can isolate the active
ingredients in various compounds various
herbs whether it is arjuna whether it is
brahmi where it is whether it is guruchi
or whatever you could you could actually
make massive
medical breakthroughs i'm sure it's
possible so india needs to take uh the
lead in this
the indian government should create
national institutes of ayurvedic
research the research should be done
using 21st century scientific methods
and all of that to be patented and
should all be branded under the umbrella
of ayurveda that's what needs to be done
so that's what i can say
next question
it won't appear
okay here it is
so this is by atma what's your take on
energy beverages is it superior to tea
um um
tea coffee contain uh
so coffee contains caffeine
which is known to be a stimulant
stimulant or i don't know what
category it falls under
uh but yeah it keeps you awake it makes
you alert and all that
so that's caffeine that's from coffee
tea contains tea in
which is which has a similar effect it
kind of perks you up it makes you more
more alert more active
but it's not as as as strong as caffeine
as far as i know yeah
so tea and coffee are both stimulants
and they they
make you more alert and all that
energy beverages don't
i think
in most energy beverages
two examples are red bull and monster
and monster energy
both of these drinks
the main
active ingredient is caffeine
i think they contain massive doses of
caffeine maybe 200 300 300 ml of
caffeine per can and that's typically
what what works you up and what gives
you the
energy as to say so to say there could
also be some other compounds like uh
citrulline malate or
beta
alanine or something like that i'm not
sure what it's called so
the they could also have some some kind
of effect of giving you some energy or
some focus things like that
there's also this this class of of
products called
pre-workout supplements
yeah that kind of uh
review op or something
i think these things uh you develop a
tolerance to that i'm sure you even
develop a tolerance to caffeine and tea
in our time
so i think uh these are
the main ingredient in most energy
beverages is anyway caffeine so i don't
think it's superior to tea or anything
people enjoy tea because tea is is rich
and complex there are so many different
varieties of tea you have green tea you
have red tea you have brown tea black
tea and all that
different flavors of tea
you can put various different spices
into tea cardamom and
various things you know there are all
these various
spice compound spice mixtures you can
add to tea and make it more aromatic
more fragrant so i think tea is a very
rich thing these energy beverages
they're like shortcuts it's like
injecting something into your body it
works for a while but
you don't get the enjoyment that people
who who are tea connoisseurs would get
out of tea
so i don't think it's superior to t
people who need a
pick me up or something could do that
you know take a shot of caffeine there
are caffeine pills available that would
work even better i suppose or just have
a black coffee or something so it's it's
at the end of the day it's all up to you
what you enjoy what you like and what
works for you yeah so i don't think
anything is superior to the other
whatever works for you is superior for
you and that's that's what matters
so it's something that's an individual
choice and preference
utmaj again i know this is not gonna get
answered but do you watch anime
nani
do i watch
not really i don't get the time
but yeah i must have watched some anime
in the past
okay that brings us to the end of
today's questions that i picked that i
picked up let's take some questions from
the live chat
a few questions from the live chat
what do we have i had many more
questions but we are almost at the end
of our time so
i'll take some live chat questions now
okay molly mv says what's the difference
between an asteroid a comet and a meteor
let me also add one more meteorite
so what's an asteroid an asteroid is a
rock that's floating around in space
it's it's orbiting the sun that's an
asteroid so you have various classes of
asteroids depending on where they're
located in the solar system you have the
standard asteroid belt between the
orbits of mass and jupiter
so you have the inner planets the
terrestrial planets which is mercury
venus earth and mars
these are the innermost orbits then you
have
an asteroid belt between the orbits of
jupiter between the orbits of mars and
jupiter that is the that's a collection
of space debris rocks
so those are called asteroids you also
have a bunch of trojan asteroids which
are at the lagrange point of jupiter
that's a whole different story so these
are essentially space rocks big space
rocks or small space rocks tiny ones
these are all called asteroids typically
an asteroid is something which is
reasonably large yeah rock size boulder
sized building sized these are asteroids
the largest asteroid we think i think is
vesta it's like small
micro my mini planet kind of thing yep
that's what an asteroid is what's a
comet a comet is
a dirty
uh snowball
it's it's
it's composed of of rubble there is some
rock there is some soot there is some
some
dust and there's a lot of
ice water snow
and there could be uh
organic compounds also in that yeah so
that's what comets are they are
essentially dirty snowballs
ice snow
and water frozen water mixed together
with some rock and some dust and some
chemical organic compounds and comets
when they are they they also orbit the
sun in various elliptical orbits some
are
small orbits some are enormous object
orbits some comets may approach the sun
once in 3000 years some in once in 80
000 years some comets go out of the sun
every few decades and so on so forth so
when they approach the sun because of
the heating effect of the of the
radiation pressure of the sun of the
solar wind the water heats up it
evaporates it produces this long tail
long tail like structure that is visible
from the earth and that's what we call
comets
what's a meteor a meteor is a space rock
that
enters the earth's atmosphere and burns
up at that atmosphere so-called shooting
stars what's a meteorite it's one of
these space rocks that doesn't burn up
but
which does burn but ends up
impacting the surface of the planet
whether it's over the oceans or on
uh ground yeah so that's the difference
between asteroid comet meteor and
meteorite
all right i hope that answers the
question
let's take one or two more questions
about science
um
uh
is is human cloning justified
i think it's unethical to to clone
humans because you are creating humans
for your own agendas and purposes human
life i mean
from the perspective of ethics
is is something that's invaluable it's
sacred you cannot mess around with it
you don't own humans if you're cloning a
human you're kind of creating a human
tailor made to your specifications and
and you're in a way owning it you hold
that person's life in your hands so to
say which is
clearly unethical so when it comes to
medical ethics human cloning is
considered to be completely unethical
and it's illegal in most places i'm sure
some nations are
tinkering with certain things but i
would i personally would consider it to
be unethical yeah so yeah i would say
it's not justified it's not something
anyone should do
um
sajad says do you think evolution really
happened well well the best evidence
that we have from the fossil record and
everything else does indicate that
evolution happened
look at the the fossil record when it
comes to human species we have
homo sapiens the oldest evidence is from
about three hundred thousand years ago
yeah the oldest
fossil evidence of homo sapiens
is was discovered in jebel
in north africa morocco i think algeria
somewhere there
three hundred thousand years ago that's
how old it is
before that we have had so many other
archaic species of humans homo erectus
homo homo habilis
harmony and arthuris homo florences and
so on so forth then he saw one also and
then you had older forms of humans uh
more archaic humans or or
australopithecus rdp takers and so on so
you can clearly see that there's
evolution happening and and the the
morphology and the shape of the bones
and and the abilities the cranial
capacity all of that is changing over
time even the eyes have moved to the
front our deep ancestors who lived like
60 60 million years ago had eyes on the
sides yeah
and so on you can see how dogs have
evolved we can see that dogs are closely
are the same species as the wolf
and the foxes are related to dogs
jackals are related to dogs
wolves
foxes dogs jackals very close together
in very similar
bears are a distant relative of dogs
seals and whales are also related to the
dogs the same extended family and you
have cats that have evolved over time so
you can see that evolution has actually
happened and you can see it go date back
millions of years even millions of years
in the fossil record so from all the
evidence
that we have of experimental evidence
hard evidence empirical evidence it does
appear
from all this evidence to the best of
our knowledge that evolution really did
happen right
okay
choose one math or physics
it's physics math is a tool as far as i
am concerned physics is what actually
makes things interesting math is about
categories and logic physics is where
you actually apply it to the real world
so for me it's physics but some people
enjoy math which is perfectly good
um okay
which branch should i take to become a
theoretical physicist in b tech
if you're doing a b tech you're doing uh
you're in a technical field
technological field you're studying to
be an engineer
if you are studying engineering you can
certainly go back into theoretical
physics but ah
i i don't know
what advice i can offer you because i
don't know you personally i don't know
what your aptitudes are what your
strengths are
if you want to become see what kind of
person becomes a good theoretical
physicist first of all you need to have
you need to be good at math
that is a given you can't do theoretical
physics without being really really good
at advanced mathematics not not basic
math really advanced mathematics yeah so
you should be able to quickly pick up
mathematical tools of number one and
secondly
you should be curious
about the mysteries of the universe
that's what theoretical physics is all
about about
unraveling and demystifying the universe
yeah
uh so
typically you would need to have the
the the the
the mindset of a detective of a very
curious detective wow look at this
mystery let's let's figure it out if you
have that approach then you would be a
good
theoretical physicist and you you may
have that curiosity
and fascination but if you are not good
at math and you still can't do it
so yeah that's what i would say first of
all you to ask yourself if you if you if
that's who you are if that's the kind of
person you have if you're doing a b tech
then you may not be able to get into
theoretical physics so typically for a
theoretical physics career you won't
need to have bsc msc then phd or
something or like that yeah
if you want to have a career within the
academic system
so yeah that's how it would go
chuching says how to have a sharp mind
and not be forgetful
um
you you cannot have a sharp mind if you
are physically unfit first of all so you
need to take care of yourself physically
stay physically active
physically fit don't eat too much don't
become obese or wait that's first thing
yeah yeah uh secondly
uh not be forgetful i am forgetful
i i forget people's names and faces all
the time
i may have met somebody five minutes ago
i
may sometimes forget people's faces
so
it's it's
someone saying eat almonds
you know
i think if you want to have a sharp mind
be curious i'm sure you are fascinated
with something or the other follow that
curiosity that fascination and when you
study stuff
always give yourself the permission to
forget stuff
give yourself the permission to forget
whatever you don't find interesting
that way you will pick up those things
you find interesting and those will be
the important things
so yeah that's that's my that's how my
approach has all been i am a very
forgetful person in
a variety of things i forget the faces
and names of most people apologies in
advance to those of you who i may meet
in the future and if i don't remember
you yeah so
some people naturally have sharp minds i
don't know i'm not one of them i forget
things but uh
stay physically fit stay physically
active if you work out regularly you're
gonna have a sharp mind for sure
eat well eat good food eat lots of
vegetables and good amount of protein
goes along with that protein of your
choice
and when you study give yourself the
permission to forget only remember what
you find interesting that way you'll do
you'll do well yeah and yeah some people
would say meditate that helps yeah
meditation also helps
and
in case you have a restless mind right
writing calms your mind down it focuses
your mind so if you have a writing habit
write a thousand words a day whatever
whatever topic
so that could sharpen your mind further
you know writing crystallizes your
thoughts and so on so yeah these are
some of the things i could tell you i
hope that helps
okay i think we are done for today we
have crossed the two hour mark as always
uh so yes yes thank you so much
for all your questions always great fun
answering your questions i apologize to
those of you whose questions are not
taken i've taken many more but i always
run out of time
so we'll keep on doing this and i will
see you very soon in the next chapter of
the ask a bit show which is tomorrow
tomorrow is a different topic
geopolitics history and current affairs
but we will keep on doing the science
sessions weekly and let's keep on doing
this thank you very much take care all
of you do very well and i will see you
in the next episode thank you bye